Preliminary Inventory of the Christian Joppke Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Christian Joppke collection,
1976-1995
94027
Joppke, Christian
10 manuscript boxes (4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Prospectus, notes, sound recordings and transcripts of interviews, photocopies of East German secret police reports, and printed articles and clippings, relating to the East German dissident movement, and to Asian and Latin American immigration to Great Britain, Germany and the United States. Used in preparation of the books by C. Joppke, East German Dissidents and the Revolution of 1989 (New York, 1994), and Immigration and the Nation-State (Oxford, 1999).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
German-American historian.
Scope and Content Note
Prospectus, notes, sound recordings and transcripts of interviews, photocopies of East German secret police reports, and printed articles and clippings, relating to the East German dissident movement, and to Asian and Latin American immigration to Great Britain, Germany and the United States. Used in preparation of the books by C. Joppke, East German Dissidents and the Revolution of 1989 (New York, 1994), and Immigration and the Nation-State (Oxford, 1999).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Dissenters--Germany (East); Germany (East)--Politics and government.; Germany--Emigration and immigration.; Great Britain--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; Germany.; Great Britain.; United States--Politics and government.
Genres and Forms of Material
Phonotapes.
Container List
- Twenty phonotape cassettes of interviews (Box 1)
- Transcripts of interviews with the following persons:
  - Apfeld (Demokratie Jetzt), 1991 June 24
  - Bartoszek, Michael (Demokratie Jetzt), 1991 June 19
  - Bohley, Bärbel (Neues Forum), 1991 July 8
  - Dahn, Daniela, 1991 June 26
  - Dusdahl (Ak Solidarische Kirche), 1991 July 26
  - Eisenfeld, Peter (bis 1987 Ökomenischer Friedenskreis Dresden), 1991 August 1
  - Ellsässer, Ralf (AG Umweltschutz), 1991 July 24
  - Fischbeck, Hans-Jürgen (DJ), 1991 July 3
  - Fischer, Werner (IFM), 1991 June 27
  - Flügge, Reiner (Demokratie Jetzt), 1991 June 18
  - Hildebrandt (Demokratie Jetzt), 1991 June 19
  - Hirsch, Ralf (IFM), 1991 July 10
  - Hülsemann, Werner (Stadtjugendpfarrer), 1991 July 1
  - Jeschonnik, Günter., See BOX 4
  - Jordan, Carlo (Netzwerk Arche), 1991 July 16
  - Klier, Freya, 1991 June 25
  - Kukutz, Irena (Frauen für den Frieden), 1991 June 24
  - Mehlhorn, Ludwig (DJ), 1991 July 3
  - Müller, Rainer (Ak Gerechtigkeit), 1991 July 24
  - Neuberg, Ehrhart, 1991 June 15
  - Pahnke, Rudi (Sekretär für kirchliche Jugendarbeit beim Bund der Evange-lischen Kirchen der DDR), 1991 June 24
  - Pflugbeil, Sebastian (Neues Forum), 1991 June 17
  - Poppe, Gerd (IFM), 1991 June 26
  - Poppe, Ulrike (Ulrike Poppe), 1991 July 9
  - Rathenow, Lutz, 1991 July 2
  - Reich, Jens (Neues Forum), 1991 July 8
  - Rüddenklau, Wolfgang (Umweltbibliothek), 1991 June 20
  - Rudolph, Thomas (Ak Gerechtigkeit), 1991 July 25
  - Schult, Reinhard (Neues Forum), 1991 July 1
  - Sellentin, Frank (IG Leben), 1991 July 26
  - Simon, Pfarrer Hans (Zionskirche), 1991 June 25
  - Strohner, Pavel (Neues Forum), 1991 June 20
  - Templin, Wolfgang (IFM), 1991 July 4
  - Walter, Katrin (Ak Gerechtigkeit), 1991 July 25
  - Wiemann, Werner (FDP/DJ), 1991 July 14
- Twenty-two phonotape cassettes (Box 2)
- Reference file
  - DDR-Literatur. Interview-Adressen
  - Literatur
- Miscellaneous photocopied articles
- Printed matter and notes (folder headings in English and German)
  - After Unification
  - Alte Opposition
  - Bürgerbewegung DDR im Herbst 1989
  - Bürgerbewegung nach 1989/90. After the Wall/ Bündnis '90
  - DDR 1989 - Exit and Voice (Box 3)
  - DDR 1989 - From Dissident to Citizen Movement
  - DDR 1989 - Regime
  - DDR Culture and Intellectuals
  - DDR-Friedensbewegung
  - DDR-Geschichte. Opposition
  - DDR - Kirche und Dissent (Box 4)
  - DDR-"Identität" / Nationale Frage
  - DDR. Old Regime, 1970s
  - Dissident Movement - Ideas
  - East Europe and Peace Movement
  - "Exit" and "Voice." Ausreiser vs. 'Opposition.'
    Includes correspondence with Albert O. Hirschman and typescript of interview with Günter Jeschonnek (1991 September 12)
  - Forum für Kirche und Menschenrechte, Nr. 1 und 2
  - GDR 1989 - A Revolution (Box 5)
  - GDR Dissident Movement
  - GDR Economy 1980s
  - GDR - Nation und Nationalismus
  - GDR Politics in the 1980s
  - Kirche und Staat in der DDR
  - Kontext. Beiträge aus Kirche & Gesellschaft · Kultur. Hrsg. von der Ev. Bekenntnisgemeinde Berlin-Treptow, 1988 November 22
  - Leipzig/Dresden
  - Menschenrechte/DDR/IFM (Box 6)
  - Ökologie
  - Peace Movement and Détente. Exit and Voice by A. Hirschman
  - Der Runde Tisch
  - Stasi
  - Stasi original [documents]
  - taz: DDD-Journal zur Novemberrevolution (Box 7)
  - taz: DDR-Journal Nr. 2: Die Wende der Wende
  - Umweltblätter
  - 'Wende' and Reunification. Diverses
  - Zeitschriften der Bürgerbewegung (Neues Forum, Demokratie Jetzt, IFM)
  - Zion/Luxemburg-Liebknecht Demonstration 1987-1988